The issue here is that it's the office
of the presidency, right? So, look, if
you have a whole bunch of intelligence
officials get getting together and a
lame duck president and setting up this
time bomb, which is really what it was,
like the this this whole thing, I think,
was designed to create this avalanche of
um problems that were that would come
down the road.
Welcome to Deep Focus. I'm John Kuryaku.
I have watched MSNBC's Morning Joe every
day for the past week, mostly so you
don't have to. Seriously though, I've
been watching Morning Joe to try to get
a sense of where the Democratic Party
stands on the issue of alleged
debunked Russian intervention in the
2016 election. You'll recall that the
Mueller report said that there was no
meaningful intervention in that
election, whether it was Russian or
otherwise. But mainstream Democrats,
including self-described progressives,
are holding to the falsehood that the
Russians somehow installed Donald Trump
as our president. Well, Director of
National Intelligence Tulsi Gabbard has
raised the issue to a higher level by
announcing an investigation into the
actions of former CIA director John
Brennan and former FBI Director Jim
Comey, both of whom pushed that Russia
narrative. Officially, the two are
alleged to have lied to Congress during
testimony on Capitol Hill. That would be
a misdemeanor and a minor misdemeanor at
that. But some Republicans are alleging
far more serious crimes. They say that
what Brennan and Comey tried to do was
to carry out what was essentially a coup
against a democratically elected
president. We're going to talk about all
this with one of the country's leading
experts on this issue, and I'm proud to
call him a friend. Matt Taibbe is an
award-winning journalist, author, and
podcaster. He's a former columnist with
Rolling Stone, where his hard-hitting
columns focused on politics, the culture
wars, and current events. And now you
can find his work both on his Substack
and at Racket News. Matt, so glad to
have you with us. Thanks for joining us.
>> No, thanks for having me back, John.
Good to see you.
>> It's good to see you, man. It always is.
Matt, wa walk us through this. Honest to
God, I thought this uh this issue was
done. It was behind us. Uh we know what
the Mueller report said. We know what
these various congressional
investigations said. And now that
there's the possibility of even minor
criminal charges against two of the
people who really pushed this narrative
the most, now we're getting this push
back from the Democrats
just asking us to forget everything we
learned over the last 8 years. What
exactly are we looking at here?
Well, I mean, criminally, I'm not sure.
Um, we know it's going to be they're
they're aiming for some kind of
conspiracy charge, but what exactly is
not clear. Uh, I've actually been trying
to find that out. Um, it's one of the
remaining mysteries in this whole thing.
But just to pull back about the
significance of what happened this week,
um, this story, and I'm I'm sure this is
probably true for you, too. This this
Russia Gate story changed my life.
Before it happened, I was a lifelong
Democrat. I had just voted for Hillary
Clinton. I was working at Rolling Stone
magazine. And then this thing happened
where suddenly we were told that the
Russians had interfered in the election
and pulled off what sounded like the
biggest intelligence coup in history,
that they had a Manurion candidate as
president-elect. Uh, and I remember
thinking as a journalist, either that's
true or this is the biggest fraud of all
time. there's really no other option.
And we went through an extraordinary
ordeal with three years of mania uh that
ended with the Mueller business uh with
no indictments and it but it was never
fully debunked. The the people who
brought the case against Trump never
admitted that it was fake, that it was a
mistake. Uh, and there was never a
reckoning like there was with the WMD
issue where at least the press admitted
that there were some screw-ups. And what
happened this week is that we finally
got a peak at the actual evidence that
they used to create this intelligence
community assessment that you and Aaron
Mate and myself and many others have
been trying to figure out. What exactly
substantiated the claim that Vladimir
Putin quote unquote aspired to help
Donald Trump because he had a quote
unquote clear preference for him and now
we know and it turns out nothing is
substantiating it and it's it's an
incredible shock. I don't know what
what's your reaction as as a former you
know intelligence person. I think this
is on the order of the WMD saying maybe
even worse
>> easily and maybe worse. You know, when I
read this account, um, I think it was at
Axios a week or so ago that John Brennan
had called together all of the the most
important, most seasoned Russia analysts
at the CIA, brought them all together to
write what was essentially a sense of
the community memorandum. Um, and then
they found that there was no Russian
interference, and then Brennan said,
"No, the analytic line is there was
Russian interference. This is what we're
going with." What shocks me is that they
didn't run physically run on Mas to the
office of the inspector general to
report him. And then just to make
matters worse when he insisted that they
add the steel dossier as an appendix to
this politicized analysis and they
refused and then he added it as an
appendix. I was disappointed again that
they didn't run to the office of the
inspector general. We shouldn't have had
to wait this long as a country to know
exactly how this played out. This is
exactly what they teach you on your very
first day at the CIA not to do
>> as an analyst. Yes.
>> If if you have somebody trying to push
you to to put an unsported claim, go to
the IG. Is that is that what you're
supposed to do?
>> It's all about evidence. And if there's
no evidence and somebody is trying to
force you to politicize the analysis,
you have to go to the inspector general
and you have to report it.
>> I mean I mean
so in in that case that makes what
happened even more egregious and and you
know there's there's new reporting even
now at the end of this week. So, there
were four major pieces of evidence that
they used to substantiate this um Putin
preferred Trump claim. And I didn't
realize this until yesterday evening um
that the the aspired line came from um a
discussion that Brennan himself had with
a Russian defector in Virginia and that
the he never put it in writing. He only
orally briefed the president. There is a
suggestion that he gave different
different accounts of that conversation
to different people. And that's in the
report. They say that that we're
concerned about this because uh the key
piece of evidence that we're hanging
this whole thing on is a discussion that
he had that John Brennan had and the the
original source is not even known where
uh this person got that from. People are
saying that it's this like small and
cuff person. Um, but that sounds like
terrible tradecraftraft to me. John, you
you tell me. Uh, you know, you don't
know where it's coming from. Like, how
can you put it in there? Well, I'll tell
you, and and forgive me if this is
getting too far down in the weeds of of
CIA analysis, but often times analysts
will be called upon to go meet with
defectors and just have a conversation.
Just see if your analysis is consistent
with their real life experience. Now, if
you write up your notes, which you're
supposed to do, you cannot use those
notes in a piece of finished
intelligence. you have to turn the notes
over to the director of operations to
what's called a a um a a cat. It's
called a reports officer and um the
reports officer puts it in a formal
channel and releases it to the entire
intelligence community. Then you can use
it because you can cite it as a source
and under on the source line it'll say
according to a recent defector or
according to an unpolyraphed source or
whatever, right? um
he just took it from from the horse's
mouth and ran with it. There's no
written evidence anywhere that anybody
ever said this. We're just supposed to
take his word for it. And that's not
analysis.
>> And it's certainly not finished
intelligence.
>> It wouldn't get into a junior high
school newspaper.
>> No way.
>> No way. And another thing too, Tucker
Carlson said a few weeks ago
>> um that he asked Putin, "Who do you
prefer?"
>> And he said, "Well, I prefer Trump to
Hillary. Trump is a little bit hard to
gauge because he changes his mind." But
he said, "Hillary, I just know I can't
work with." Okay, that's not top secret,
you know, Russian government
information. He just came out with it. A
journalist asked him a question, he gave
an answer. There it is. No big mystery.
Right. Right. But but
>> there's a difference between that and
they interfered with active measures to
help to to help uh Donald Trump. And at
that time Trump was a political un more
of a political unknown and from what I
understand reading the accounts that
they had they had significant
intelligence going in both directions
saying that on the one hand yes they
would have preferred uh a Republican
candidate uh because they're Republicans
have traditionally historically it's
easier to make deals with them. They're
less concerned about human rights. Um,
but there was also intelligence saying
that Trump was mirial. He was
unpredictable. Uh, with Hillary, we at
least know where she stands. Uh, you
know, we think that it either way we're
well positioned to outmaneuver. That was
the quote. That's a direct quote from
from Putin. By the way, this is the
other thing about the report that came
out. And just for for background, what
we're talking about is this House
Intelligence Committee report that's
been locked away for uh since 2018 at
Langley. Um
apparently
um
no, they they they had almost no good
intelligence at all about Russia. That's
one of the things that's striking about
>> that's an ongoing theme,
>> right? So you're reading this and you're
like, "Wow, they they just don't have a
lot of penetration at you would think if
you if there was more stuff they could
manipulate it, right?" Right.
>> But they they did. One thing jumps out
in the report is that they have a what
they call significant intelligence from
a confidant of Vladimir Putin and he's
quoting Putin directly and Putin is
saying I don't really care who wins e
either either way and no matter what
this we're not going to have good
relations with the United States that
they're not interested in it but we
think we're pos well we're well
positioned to outmaneuver uh either
candidate and then and that he would uh
recount the flow of both of them. So,
but they suppressed that. So, they used
they used the unsourced, unverified
steel dossier and Brennan's whatever
conversation, but they suppressed that.
That sounds like good intelligence to
me.
>> It actually sounds like pretty good
intelligence. Yeah. And again, this is
exactly what they teach you at the farm
in the in the analytic tradecraftraft
course not to do. Not to do. You and I
had a conversation ages ago about the
Steel Dossier,
>> and I I remember part of the
conversation being
that you can't blame Chris Steele
>> for this complete screw-up on the
American side because Chris Steele was a
collector. He was a case officer and his
job is to just cast a wide net, ask his
sources questions A, B, C, and D, and
then report back on what their answers
are. And then it's the analyst's job to
vet the answers and you know present the
final analysis to whomever the consumer
happens to be. In this case it was the
Clinton campaign. Well
to cherrypick intelligence and say like
oh my god uh Trump hired prostitutes to
pee on the bed that Donald Trump slept
in. That's not that's not intelligence.
That's just a rumor that somebody threw
out and and Steel reported it back and
said, you know, you can take it or leave
it, but this is what people are telling
me. I'm not the expert here. You guys
are the experts. So, here's what I've
collected. But they didn't take the the
they didn't make their own analysis.
They didn't take the best of the
intelligence. They just went with what
was ugliest and then pointed the finger
at the Trump campaign and pointed the
finger at Vladimir Putin and said they
were in bed together.
It was intellectually dishonest.
>> Oh, ex extremely right. I mean, but I
think there's still some mystery about
why they did that. Like to me, it feel
it feels to me like they wanted to
investigate Trump. this this for the f
from the FBI side the the utility would
have been using it to get a FISA warrant
on Carter Page but then you know later
on suddenly
you know it they have to go to Broadway
uh with this whole thing and there there
there's apprehension they they tell the
New York Times to back off of it just
before the election they don't endorse
it publicly and then all of a sudden
that there's this moment just before um
you you know the second week in December
there just December 9th
2016 where all of the sudden they get
ordered to do this new assessment and
they they they all have to publicly back
it. Don't you think there had to be some
kind of thing that happened to justify
all of those chiefs getting behind it?
>> There there has to be there has to be.
And you know, we we have heard the
rumors about Maniffort and his contacts
with the Russians or with somebody who
who happened to be a Russian um
intelligence officer. We heard about the
screw up uh involving Carter Page. I
actually spoke to Carter Page about it
and he's still very bitter
>> that that they tried to sacrifice him
for this political goal. But with all
that said,
there's never really been any justice
for people wrongly accused. You know, um
George Papadopoulos is another example.
George went to prison for, I don't know,
6 weeks or whatever it was and um and
tried to rehabilitate himself by running
for Congress. He was unsuccessful. He's
out there on the speaking circuit. But
there's never been an apology to George
Papopoulos. There's never been anybody
to come forward and say, "Wow, we really
did this guy wrong. You know, we owe him
an apology."
Never. In fact, if you just watch
Morning Joe in the morning, they're all
doubling down and they're they're asking
us and I I would laugh it if it wasn't
so serious. They're asking us to just
forget everything we've learned in the
past several years and go back like
default back to their original
accusations. I I think I mentioned to
you one time that um back in 20 uh 2017,
a cousin of mine um uh set me up on a
blind date and
lovely lovely woman. She happened to be
an attorney for the DNC
and we were at this bar having a drink
and she looked me right in the eye and
she said, "I believe in my heart that
the first thing Donald Trump does when
he wakes up in the morning is he calls
Vladimir Putin on the hotline to get his
instructions for the day." And I
laughed.
>> And then I said I said, "Oh my god, are
you serious?"
And she said, "Yes, he's a Manurion
candidate."
>> Wow.
>> And I said, "Yeah, this isn't going to
work."
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. This isn't going to work. She was
very nice. But but you know, that was
the first indication that I had that
>> that oh my god, people actually believe
this.
>> Oh, I thought it was just a political
thing. We're going to go out there and
we're going to really screw them. And
no, they believe this.
>> Evidence be damned.
Yeah. And and and
it was obviously it wre tremendous havoc
with the news media business too. I mean
there were a lot of us who were kind of
pushed out and never never came back in.
Right. like um this story I I think
people underestimate what a major
dividing line in American society this
story was because
uh it was a gigantic PR/advertising
campaign and I to this day I think the
major schism in American society is
between people who believe it and people
who who came not to believe it. Right?
There were obviously sort of Trump
partisans who resisted it for other
reasons, but there's a significant
population of people who were
disenchanted over the years and also
because of other things that happened
with COVID, right? Where they realized
they were being lied to. But this is the
big one. This was the one where they
they threw they said, "Trust us, we all,
you know, all 17 agencies, right? Like
we're we're all behind it." And then it
turns out it's not 17, it's three. Then
it turns out this week that it's not
three, it's one. Uh, and you know, and
it's not even really one agency, it's
one guy. It's John Brennan who had one
conversation and it's a a fragment from
that. That's
>> it's like a joke. Like you you if
Jonathan Swift wrote this, he couldn't
have done a better job. It's it's that
ridiculous.
>> Matt, when I was still at the CIA uh in
2004,
I was in the director of operations. My
wife was in the directorate of
intelligence, so she was an analyst. She
was actually a very senior analyst. And
she came home one day and she said, "Did
you hear about the president's new
order?" And I said, "No." And she said,
"He ordered us to add a paragraph to all
of our analysis for the president's
daily brief." I wasn't following. Well,
she says, you know, that the president's
daily brief, you have fact and then you
have analysis, right? She says, 'Now we
have to add a third paragraph, which is
policy recommendation. And I said, 'Oh
my god, that's a violation of the CIA's
charter. You can't make a Yeah, you
can't make a policy recommendation. The
whole idea of intelligence is you
present the intelligence to the to the
policy makers with the best informed
analysis and then they make the policy
decision. But here's the president
saying, "Okay, so tell me the news. tell
me what the news means and then tell me
what I should do. Like, it's not the
CIA's
purview to tell the president of the
United States what he should do, but
that's exactly what happened in this
case. And to make it worse,
the recommendation was based on a lie.
>> Yeah. I mean obviously and that and
that's very ironic that story because
that really mirrors the exact same
development in journalism where
you know our mandate was find the stuff
get it together put it out let the
public figure it out right um now we
have to have the message here's how you
should take this
>> yeah I hate that so much
>> right and
>> here's what you need to know it's like
no you no you don't tell me what I need
to know lay out the story and I decide
what I need to know,
>> right?
>> I hate that so much.
>> And as and as you know, like finding out
the stuff is is a pretty hard job
already like you know and you ask all
these B minus or C++ brains to try to
come up with well what does it mean and
what should we do about it? I think
that's just taxing them beyond their
capabilities. And you I think we see
that very clearly with this Russia story
where, you know, it's a combination of
incompetence, inertia, but also clearly
at the root of it, deep corruption. I
mean, I I don't know the bottom line
what the the what prompted this order uh
why
>> Barack Obama suddenly decided to
commission this assessment. Um but
whatever it is, it's a bad reason. I
mean, unless he was deeply misinformed
about the seriousness of the
intelligence, um I can't there's no
innocent explanation I can come up with.
Is is there that you can say?
>> No. Makes no sense to me at all.
Especially when when Obama was a lame
duck and he was he was leaving anyway,
>> right?
>> It just doesn't make any sense unless
you know John Brennan when I was still
at the agency.
John Brennan was was pretty senior by
then. He had been the executive
director. He had been the first head of
the transnational terrorism information
center which became the National
Counterterrorism Center. but he was
telling everybody who would listen back
then that he wanted to be secretary of
defense. So he had this interim stop as
CIA director under under um Obama, but
he was ready to move up to SEC death.
And I wonder if that's what the
motivation was
>> that that he wanted that other job. So
he was going to be absolutely
indispensable to a president Hillary
Clinton.
>> I see. Right.
>> Or whoever happened to follow her.
>> Well, that makes a lot of sense. Uh and
Obama obviously would have trusted
Brennan or probably was politically
deeply in debt to him. I mean, Brennan
was the first big
>> Yeah.
>> name in the intelligence community to
back him.
>> That's right. So, you know, but I just
don't understand what that transaction
was because they they were on course to
kind of let it let it go. Like all the
Crossfire uh investigations had kind of
petered out by then. They didn't really
have any more leads. So, all to suddenly
just floor it and order this thing with
this incredibly aggressive conclusion.
And the leaking too, that's the other
thing that's shocking about this. like
when you see the the one of the things
that Tulsa released this week um were
the actually it was over last weekend
were the emails talking about the from
the DNI
uh saying you know per request of the
president you we're all going to have to
get together and put together this new
assessment and it's dated like December
9th and we're going to find out what
happened. Well, while they're uh giving
that assignment to find out what
happened, they're that very minute
they're leaking to the New York Times
and Washington Post who put out stories
that night. So, they already clearly had
the conclusion and this was just for
show. Um, and which is just shocking to
me like but they they say they so
aggressively came out with this. Also,
it's it speaks I mean it's obviously a
huge indictment of the news
organizations that just ran it,
>> right?
>> And and I'll add as an aside, it's also
a violation of the Espionage Act.
>> Is it?
>> Yeah. In in my case, the judge set a
precedent by defining espionage as
providing national defense information
to any person not entitled to receive
it. Period.
And so if the information when it was
leaked to the Times and the Post hadn't
been formally declassified,
that's an act of espionage.
>> Oo, that is interesting.
That is very interesting. Do you think
that might be u one of this one of the
>> I've been thinking about it for the last
couple of days. That's why I was so
excited to have you on because because
you you go so deep on on these issues
and I was disappointed to see at least
in the initial reporting that what the
criminal referral was to the Justice
Department was that they had lied in
their testimony uh on Capitol Hill.
Well, that's a misdemeanor and it calls
for zero jail time. It calls for like 12
months probation, I think, uh for a
first time offense.
But if we're talking about conspiracy,
which is what they're talking about this
week, or even better, if if the word
espionage creeps into the national
conversation, then it's a whole new
ballgame. And I was just wondering if
you had heard anything about
about what crimes they may be looking to
charge. We're not really seeing
reporting on it, at least not in the
mainstream media, but people have to be
talking about it at least at some level.
>> So there there's a lot of chatter about
it. Um I'm sure you saw um Devin Nunees
this week was was talking about the Mara
Lago raid and intimating that
>> that was somehow tied to all of this,
>> right? There are a lot of stories being
circulated about people in um in Trump's
2024 campaign who were um
placed under investigation allegedly
uh and surveiled and that there so
there's a there there are there are
rumors that there are they're going to
allege a pattern of conduct
um you know to jin up Russia gate and
then conduct phony political
surveillance. So violation of maybe
FISA, you know, that that could be in
there. I mean, but the Espionage Act,
what you're saying, that makes a lot of
sense, too. The because leaking is
clearly a huge part of this whole thing
and and that was a consistent
>> feature of this entire scandal. They and
they didn't just do it in one time. They
they did it repeatedly. Uh so I mean
they and they leaked signals
intelligence, right? Like they they
leaked all kinds of stuff, you know,
this stuff that even journalists aren't
allowed to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
and so I wonder if it's that. I don't
know. I mean the leaking about leaking
the FISA court results like I I mean
they already charged that.
>> Um and they had one case involving that
Senate aid, the head of security. Yeah,
the head of security. That's right.
>> But but there has there's got to be more
meat on that bone, I think. And there's
more. So,
>> that's right. There has to be. I will
warn these these guys.
>> If you think you're under surveillance,
you probably are.
>> And I I'll give you an example.
>> In January of 2012, my mom's sister
died. So, uh, the funeral was going to
be in Western Pennsylvania where I grew
up. And so I got in the car and I drove
up there.
Warren, Ohio is where my mom and her
brothers and sisters were all born. And
it's only 20, 30 minutes drive from my
hometown. So I thought, I'm going to go
to the cemetery and put flowers at my
grandparents graves and drive by the old
house and just see it. So I go to the
house and I pull over to the side of the
road and I noticed there's a guy behind
me. So, I rolled down my window and I
went like this, you know, to wave and
pass me because I'm just going to stop
and and look at the house for a minute.
But he didn't pass me. He just sat there
behind me. And I thought, "Okay, that's
weird, but all right." I drive up to the
end of the block and I make a big
illegal U-turn in the intersection. And
then he makes the big illegal U-turn.
So, I call my wife in DC and I said,
"I'm under surveillance. I'm sure that I
am." And she said, 'Oh, come on.' I
said, 'N no, I'm sure.' And I told her
what I just told you. She said, 'Well,
what are you doing now? I said, 'I'm
going to drive over to the cemetery. If
he follows me into the cemetery, I'm
going to confront him. So, I drive over
to the cemetery. And it's like this 19th
century cemetery that still has a little
bit of room, and that's where everybody
goes in the news section. So, I pull in.
He pulls in behind me. I go to my
grandparents graves. I put the flowers.
I stand there for a couple of minutes.
And then I thought, "Ah, my my ex-in-law
is back in the uh in the back part. I'm
going to drive back there." He follows
me. So, finally, I get out of my car and
I was like, "What? What are you doing?"
And he takes off.
I was arrested 4 days later.
>> Oh, okay. All right. And it turned out
we we saw in Discovery,
>> they didn't know that my aunt died.
>> They thought somebody had leaked to me
that they were going to arrest me and
that I was running to Canada.
[Laughter]
>> Morons.
>> That's embarrassing.
>> So my my message to these people who are
under surveillance, if you think you're
under surveillance, you are. Relax.
>> You probably are. Yes.
>> Call a lawyer,
>> right? call a lawyer. Uh well, I mean
that's that's terrifying. I mean,
did having gone through this though,
uh what's the significance of,
you know, for instance, a CIA director
being under criminal investigation or an
FBI director, is that something that
could ever realistically
happen? Um like they the the pattern is
they they go after somebody like you and
Right. I mean
>> well they they've gone after they went
after John Deutsch.
>> Um I mean he
>> he took his CIA laptop home. He
essentially stole it so he could write
his his memoirs and look at classified
documents to remind him of stories. And
he ended up taking a plea. They they
bargained it down to a misdemeanor which
they always do. Sandy Burgerer is
another one. He was the national
security adviser. He went to the
national archives to the classified
reading room.
>> Oh, didn't he stuff something in his
shirt?
>> In his underwear underwear, right?
>> Classified documents.
>> They also pushed that down to a
misdemeanor. Um, I'm unaware of any FBI
director ever being in that kind of
trouble. But
this seems to be such an assault on
democracy
that if if there's a crime that's been
committed and a crime that will be
charged, it's got to be a felony, right?
I mean, what we're talking about here,
seriously,
is an attempted coup.
>> I think that that's what we're talking
about.
>> I've used that word before for this and
I think it's appropriate. I mean like
too
>> the
>> when the four intelligence chiefs see
Yeah, remember they they do this
intelligence community assessment, they
stick the steel stuff in there that they
know is fake. Uh then they've had
trouble, right, generating
uh press around
the whole blackmail angle, all the
salacious stuff, but they can't just put
it out there either because they don't
want to be the sources for it, right?
>> So what do they do? They put it in the
annex. Then they then the news leaks
that there's a briefing, right? And I
while they're still investigating him
like the the the Comey talking about how
he was investigating Trump's reaction to
being presented with this. I think that
that's some kind of weird like
insubordination. Yes. Right. Is
>> I have to agree. I have to agree. And
the buck has to stop somewhere.
Right? Otherwise, we have chaos. Chaos
at the top echelons of government and we
can't live like that.
>> And I think people, one of the things
that's distracting for people is that
they just don't like Donald Trump or
it's they think, well, even if he didn't
do that, he must have done something.
Well, you can't do that. Like, this is
>> the issue here is that it's the office
of the presidency, right? So look, if
you have a whole bunch of intelligence
officials get getting together and a
lame duck president and setting up this
time bomb, which is really what it was,
like the this this whole thing, I think,
was designed to create this avalanche of
um problems that were that would come
down the road. Uh you know, there were
news stories uh coming out. I remember
there was a story in Harets saying from
MSAD sources saying the United States is
has told us not to share intelligence
um with the new president, right? Uh
think think about the implications of
doing that to your own country, right?
like you're you're uh advertising to the
world that uh you know a foreign power
is now in control of the White House.
That's I mean it's it's not a crime.
That's one of the things like I talked
to to one of the people kind of around
this investigation who was saying there
isn't a crime for what these guys did.
It's like it's so it's so big that uh
it's not really described. But you're
right. It has whatever it is has to be a
felony. It's got to be It's got to be a
felony. Yeah, I think so, too. Um I I'd
love to get your thoughts, too, on these
on these attacks against u uh Tulsi
Gabbard. Again, Morning Joe, they
evviscerate her. They call her um
well-known conspiracy theorist Tulsi
Gabbard.
Well, I I follow Tulsi Gabbard. I follow
these issues. I'm not seeing any
promotion of a conspiracy.
>> It's I mean they should know they're the
promoters of the conspiracy theory. If
you go back and look, I think it's
February 2nd of 2019
when she announced her run for the
presidency. It was a weekend. uh NBC and
MSNBC
timed a gigantic hit piece uh that was
going to assert that she she was the new
favorite of the Kremlin to the date of
the launch of her presidential run. And
if you look and see who the sources are
in that story, it's fascinating.
Remember you and I talked about Hamilton
68.
>> Sure.
>> Uh so it's the Hamilton 68 people. It's
a new knowledge uh whose CEO was the
creator of the Hamilton 68 dashboard and
then Clint Watts who was a an FBI agent
but who was the public face of uh the
Alliance for Securing Democracy, this
Hamilton 68 project. Uh, and they set
her up with basically phony
intelligence, you know, like like they
were using the whole bots are following
uh Tulsi Gabbard uh thing to to make her
look like a, you know, some kind of
favorite of the Russians. And then, you
know, for Hillary Clinton to come out
later and call her a favorite and and a
Russian asset.
>> A Russian asset. Very pointed words.
Those words have real meaning in the
intelligence community. It means that
you are taking money from the Russian
government to report back to them
classified information. That was
defamatory
>> and and does it also mean taking
direction too? Like I was unclear about
that.
>> Yes. So
>> yes.
>> So
>> yeah, I mean that's
absolutely defamatory. She lost that
action if I remember correctly, right?
She sued. Yes.
>> But yeah, so NBC is complicit in this
whole thing as far as I'm concerned.
like for for them to come out and call
her a conspiracy theorist. And you know,
I I I I know Tulsa a little bit. I I I
covered her campaign. I saw her around
that time um in New Hampshire a little
bit before that. And um I I think it
affected her deeply that this happened.
I mean, you can um as you know, like if
you serve your country and then they
turn around and they you make claims
about you, uh it's it's you know, it
cuts you to the the core. And then she
finds out, of course, that she's under
surveillance.
>> Yeah.
>> Through this crazy TSA program um last
>> I forgot about that.
>> Yeah.
>> Yes, you're right.
>> The Quiet Skies program. Um, and you
know, when I found out about that, I I
was stunned that this thing even exists,
like for people who don't know, the you
can have as many as 15 people in an
airport following a single person. Uh,
and it's it's three marshals per person
per flight, uh, with dogs and everything
like that. And you don't have to be even
accused of a crime. There's there's no
predication that's necessary for you.
You just have to there's some kind of
thing where if you if you show up in the
same room with somebody else who's in
who's on some kind of list, like you get
on it automatically.
>> Oh my god.
>> So, um yeah, if I were in her shoes, I I
understand. You can you can tell that
she's mad in the right. So,
>> yeah.
>> Um and which actually she should be. She
has every right to be. And that actually
leads to my next question.
Do you envision
this moving with some speed or are we
going to have to start facing
congressional investigations and you
know a two-year long uh DOJ
investigation and subpoenas and because
it seems to me that
that this could go either way depending
on politically how they want it to to
unfold.
I think it's going to end up with a
special prosecutor is my guess. Um,
obviously Cash Patel has put together
cases before.
That's this th this is the case that got
him this job. Uh, and I imagine he would
want to be personally involved, but I
can't imagine being FBI director and
personally doing the case. There's no
way, right? So, um, you know, they
they've put together a team.
I think there's some confusion from what
I understand as to, you know, what
they're going to charge or what they're
going to try to charge. Uh, but
it's probably going to be a process for
sure. But the thing is, the one
advantage that they have is that most of
the stuff has already been done. The
only the only thing that's that that's
outstanding would be um interviews with
people who previously refused. Uh there
were 30 people that this uh House Intel
Committee group tried to interview who
said no apparently at the direction of
Andrew McCabe. Um and so the there's a
little bit of work to be done there, but
almost everything else is on paper. Uh
and so I don't know. What do you think?
I'm curious to know what you like. I'm
not a lawyer, so you know.
>> Yeah. And nor am I. But I think you're
right here. I think that
I think that Donald Trump is serious
about prosecuting and because he's
serious about prosecuting, he's going to
want it to go off without a hitch. And
you do that by appointing a special
prosecutor or whatever they call it now,
special counsel. Um, I think you're also
right in that a lot of the leg work has
been done and the information is, you
know, it's still relevant and so I think
a special prosecutor will be named. I
think that Republicans will be told by
the White House to stop talking about
this and let the let the prosecutors do
their job. And I think we're going to
see felony charges in the end. They may
be process charges, but still felonies.
>> Well, look, uh, I'll take it. Right.
Yeah, me too. Frankly,
>> because even just to see people admit
the truth of it. Um, one other thing I
wanted to ask you about, uh, there's a
really fascinating detail that kind of
came out this week in this report. um in
this report as well as a declassified
annex to um the midyear exam I IG
investigation.
The one of the things that the this
declassified house intel committee
report says is that there was a a huge
trove of hacked information that
apparently the Russians had.
>> I saw that. and and the uh the
implication of the report was Putin had
a lot more stuff that he could have
released if he had wanted to. And uh
this contradicted the previous report
that said um you know that he he had uh
when possible uh helped Donald Trump. So
it it turns out that this material that
they're talking about is the same
material that was at issue in the
Clinton email investigation. the stuff
that was delivered back to the United
States by this source they're calling
T1. And it's eight thumb drives worth of
stuff, mostly correspondents from
American politicians,
a lot of DNC correspondents, but also
Obama's office, State Department. How
big of a security failure is eight thumb
drives worth of American correspondents
all the way up to the president? like
yeah it would story is it
>> gigantic yeah enormous and again again
again I come back to the to the
espionage act definition
>> you know this is something that that
Jason Leopold and I discussed after he
broke the story and I said oh this is an
espionage act case he said well how do
you figure if if if
nobody else had access to the to the
server and it was in her basement or
whatever it was how how would that be an
espionage act case and And I said, "She
has house staff. She has a cleaning
lady, a cook, uh maybe an an intern that
doesn't have access up to uh top secret
sitkma
uh information. Anybody who may have
walked past her desk when a classified
document was sitting on it is providing
national defense information to any
person not entitled to receive it." So,
it's one of these situations where
they're not going to charge it 99 times
out of 100, but if they really want to
get you and they want to be serious
about it, they'll charge it.
>> Well, in that case, I mean, they got
like she directed that person from that
Denverbased company that was doing the
work to delete delete all of her stuff.
So,
>> right. Um,
and but it's just striking to me that
that there had to be other people who
mishandled that material as well.
>> Absolutely.
>> And um I I I just don't understand why
that I guess it's because it it's part
of the Clinton email investigation and
people have kind of written it off as oh
but her emails, but it's it's not about
Hillary Clinton to me. It's just it's
about the fact that
there was that big of a security
failure,
>> right?
It seems like that that would be a
serious thing to look at.
>> Oh, man. I agree. I agree.
>> So, anyway,
>> there are standards. They have to be
standards for everybody. I I feel very
strongly about that.
>> Definitely.
>> Well, Matt, we'll uh we'll end it there.
I want to thank you again for for being
with us. It's always such a a treat to
have you.
>> Thanks so much, John. I really
appreciate you having me on and good
luck with the show and uh talk to you
soon.
>> Thank you. Matt Taibbe is an
award-winning journalist, author, and
podcaster. He's a former columnist with
Rolling Stone. And now you can find his
work both on his Substack and at Racket
News. And as always, ladies and
gentlemen, thank you so much for joining
us. Please do me that favor of hitting
the subscribe and like button. Share it.
Tell your friends. I appreciate it very
much. Take care.